This is 1KMO, we are starting on the middle of ל"ב עמוד
ב'. Lamed Bet Amud Bet. We are in the middle of the
fact that the distinction between טרפות Treifas and נבילה Neveila is that
a נבילה Neveila is an animal that died without the benefit of
שחיטה, Shechita, which also means that the שחיטה Shechita was ruined, you
know, was messed up in the process, whereas a טריפה Treifa is
an animal that got a שחיטה Shechita but had some type of
internal injury. Now, or external, but anyway now, the גמרא Gemara has
been very troubled by the fact that in the list of טרפות
Treifas there are animals with holes in their esophagus and cut tracheas
because the גמרא Gemara assumes, and we will see in a minute
today that it actually is going to conclude, it assumes that with
a cut trachea and esophagus you can never do a good שחיטה.
Shechita. Once one of those סימנים Simanim is damaged, any שחיטה Shechita
is not meaningful for it. So how come that's called an animal
when it has those problems called a טריפה, Treifa, it will always
be a נבילה? Neveila?
And the גמרא's Gemara answer that it seemed most satisfying yesterday that
we ended with was well it matters if the שחיטה Shechita incorporated
the cut. If there was a cut in the trachea or esophagus
and you shechted at a different location, it's a good שחיטה Shechita
and an external problem, a cut which makes it a טריפה. Treifa.
If you shechted where this cut existed, then it became incorporated into
your שחיטה Shechita and made the שחיטה Shechita no good. Okay, that's
where we left off yesterday and that's where we continue today. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this. The line starts with the word
לפסול. Lipasel. It is I would say almost twenty lines from the
bottom.
לפסול דמיא Lipasel Damya is the first two words in the line.
ומי אמר רבי שמעון בן לקיש הכי? Umi Amar Rabbi Shimon Ben
Lakish Hachi? Did רבי שמעון בן לקיש Rabbi Shimon Ben Lakish really
say this that it matters whether you shecht in the place where
there's the cut or not the cut? והאמר רבי שמעון בן לקיש,
Veha’amar Rabbi Shimon Ben Lakish, we know רבי שמעון בן לקיש Rabbi
Shimon Ben Lakish said שחט את הקנה, Shachat et Hakaneh, if you
shechted the
trachea ואחר כך ניקבה הריאה, Ve'achar kach nikva hareiah,
and then the lung got a hole in it. So now we
are entering an interesting question. Yesterday the question was raised let's say
the animal becomes a טריפה Treifa after שחיטה Shechita before it dies
and I say no problem once it's shechted it's meat, it's permissible
even if it's still alive, it can't be a טריפה. Treifa. What
if it becomes a טריפה Treifa between the first and the second
סימן? Siman? You got to love these questions in the גמרא, Gemara,
right? So between the first... do we say you started the process
of שחיטה Shechita and now becoming a טריפה Treifa is irrelevant or
do we say no, you know, it's still not done with the
שחיטה, Shechita, maybe this is part of a question of יש לשחיטה
מתחילה ועד סוף, Yesh lishchita mitichila ve'ad sof, you're still not done
with the שחיטה, Shechita, so if it becomes a טריפה Treifa now
it is a problem. So here that could be a general question.
What if it becomes a טריפה Treifa between the first and the
second סימן? Siman? Here it's even more specific. It got a hole
in the lung after you cut the trachea. So there is no
more relevance of the lung to the life of the animal once
the trachea is cut. So maybe there, let's say for example I
made it an even easier question. You cut the trachea and then
it got a hole in another part of the trachea. So you
would obviously say of course that's not relevant, the trachea's already cut,
that can't make it anymore of a problem. So similarly you cut
the trachea and then you got a hole in the lung, it's
all part of the same you know unit and so there's no
value to the lung anymore. So therefore says ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
that certainly will
not make it a
טריפה.
Treifa. Yes, the hole in the lung from shechting? What? The hole
in the lung didn't come from shechting?
It didn't come from shechting, it came there was a pin lodged
inside the animal and somehow it punctured it exactly or maybe it
did come from shechting, who knows, but it happened after you cut
the trachea. Okay, so therefore ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says והאמר רבי
שמעון בן לקיש שחט את הקנה ואחר כך ניקבה הריאה
כשרה. Veha’amar Rabbi Shimon Ben Lakish shachat et hakaneh ve'achar kach nikva
hareiah keshera. It's כשרה Keshera because the lung is now irrelevant. אלמא,
Alma, so what do you see from this? כמאן דמנחא בדיקולא דמיא.
Keman demancha bedikula damya.
Once the trachea is cut, it's like that whole apparatus, the trachea
with the lung, is like it is placed in a basket, meaning
it's no longer part of the life of the animal and that's
why a hole in the lung we can say is irrelevant because
the lung has been rendered irrelevant and it's like that whole organ
has been removed. So once that's true that once the trachea is
cut it's like the whole organ has been removed, says the גמרא,
Gemara, הכא נמי כמאן דמנחא בדיקולא דמיא. Hacha nami keman demancha bedikula
damya. And this reveals the גמרא's Gemara assumption from the very beginning
of the דף Daf that I think we had a problem with.
Once that organ is injured and made a טריפה, Treifa, once there's
a cut in the trachea not because of your שחיטה Shechita but
there's a cut in the trachea or a cut in the esophagus,
it's like that organ is no longer functional and it's like that
organ is no longer part of the animal. And if that's true,
how can you claim to be doing a שחיטה Shechita on an
animal that has a damaged trachea or a damaged esophagus? So the
גמרא Gemara again you could have made a distinction perhaps between these
but the גמרא Gemara is saying the same way the cut in
the trachea renders a hole in the... long irrelevant, that shows that
once the thing is cut it's like it's no longer there, and
therefore you can no longer do a שחיטה shechita on it. So
we're back to our question: how can we say that a hole
in the trachea, a hole in the esophagus makes something a טריפה
treifa if here we're assuming that it makes it as if that
organ isn't present, and therefore you can't do a שחיטה shechita on
the trachea or the esophagus? It's like it's no longer there. So
the גמרא Gemara thinks that that's very persuasive logic, and the גמרא
Gemara actually says, you know what? You're right. So here's the גמרא'ס
Gemara's answer: אלא אמר רבי חייא בר אבא רבי חייא בר אבא
אמר רבי יוחנן Ela amar Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba, Rabbi Chiyya bar
Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan לא קשיא, lo kashya, you know what? It's
not difficult, or really it is difficult, but here I'm going to
answer it. כאן קודם חזרה כאן לאחר חזרה ומשנה לא זזה ממקומה.
kan kodem chazara, kan le'achar chazara, umishna lo zaz mi'mekomah. Here it's
before the retraction, there it's after the retraction, but the משנה Mishna
was not removed from its place. What does that mean? Remember in
our משנה, Mishna, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva does not agree, started by
saying that an animal could be a טריפה treifa even if you
ruin the שחיטה. shechita. Maybe he assumed a נבלה neveila was only
when it died naturally, but he assumed that a ruined שחיטה shechita
is still a טריפה. treifa. Then he retracted himself. So the גמרא'ס
Gemara's saying, you know what? You're right. If it's got a cut
trachea, cut esophagus, it can never be a good שחיטה, shechita, and
it'll be a נבלה. neveila. How about the משנה Mishna in the
beginning of the next פרק perek that calls it a טריפה? treifa?
That was רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva before he retracted himself. When רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva originally said that a ruined שחיטה shechita is a
טריפה, treifa, that's when it mentioned a cut trachea, cut esophagus is
a טריפה. treifa. But now that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva has retracted
himself and would say that a bad שחיטה shechita is a נבלה,
neveila, so a cut trachea, cut esophagus is a bad שחיטה, shechita,
makes it a bad שחיטה, shechita, makes the animal a נבלה, neveila,
we just did not change the משנה. Mishna. משנה לא זזה ממקומה.
mishna lo zaz mi'mekomah. Once that משנה Mishna was taught, we preserve
that text even though based on later rulings, you know, that text
was no longer accurate. Based on רבי עקיבא'ס Rabbi Akiva's retraction, that
text should have been revised, that משנה Mishna should have been revised,
but we left the משנה Mishna the way it was originally taught.
So in the conclusion, the גמרא Gemara actually says, you know what?
You're right. Once the trachea or the esophagus is made into a
טריפה, treifa, that actually means that it is completely considered as if
it might as well not be there. You can't do a שחיטה
shechita on it,
and the animal in that case will become a נבלה. neveila. Very
surprising, but that is actually the conclusion of the גמרא. Gemara. Yes,
Michael, you had...
I think you remember that when we're doing this there was some
sort of שיטה shita like this before and I thought it was
just they had assumed unless they expanded it, there was just one
of them that really makes it a טריפה treifa or the other
or...
No, the question is the degree. The hole in the... oh, no,
there was a question about the birds. Certainly the esophagus is more
central, bizarrely, in the גמרא, Gemara, so a hole in the esophagus
is a טריפה treifa or now we see eventually will become a
נבלה, neveila, whereas by the trachea you need the majority to be
cut. And because the esophagus was seen as more central, the גמרא
Gemara thought that maybe when one suffices by a bird, maybe it'd
have to be the esophagus, but in the end the גמרא Gemara
rejected that.
So in the end it really makes no difference, one or the
other and...
Yes, except that still the esophagus is seen as a little more
central because, or a little more vital, because even a hole in
the esophagus makes it a טריפה treifa and eventually a נבלה, neveila,
whereas by a trachea a hole would not do so, you need
a majority. Majority cut, exactly. That's why it says נקובת הוושט ופסוקת
הגרגרת nekuvat ha'veshet u'psukat ha'gargeret or הגרגרת, ha'gargeret, excuse me, yeah.
In other words the שחיטה shechita is the initial cutting of the
knife contact with
the live animal. Right. So in other words if it comes from
cut from somewhere else,
in other words you still wouldn't have the majority you'd have...
Well, if the cut was not the majority of the קנה, kaneh,
remember the גמרא Gemara had this case that it revisited a few
times, which is the minority of the trachea was cut and then
you continued cutting, right, and that actually becomes a good שחיטה. shechita.
But once the trachea or the esophagus is cut to the point
where the animal is considered a טריפה, treifa, that means that that
organ might as well not be there. And therefore, the next logical
step, says the גמרא, Gemara, is that you can never do a
good שחיטה shechita on it
and it becomes a נבלה. neveila. Now, interestingly, right, you could, I
don't know why the גמרא Gemara didn't answer this because the later
משנה Mishna is talking about בהמה, behema, large animals, but you could
have a cut on the trachea or the esophagus with a טריפה
treifa by a bird, because you only have to cut the other
סימן. siman. So if you have the trachea cut but you do
a שחיטה shechita on the esophagus, or the esophagus cut and you
do a שחיטה shechita on the trachea, so fine, let it be
like the other סימן siman is not there.
The שחיטה shechita only requires one סימן. siman. So in that case
you could actually have that it has those, one of those problems
and it's a טריפה treifa not a נבלה. neveila. But with animals,
since you need to cut both and it's like one of them
no longer exists, it will have to be a נבלה, neveila, you'll
never do a good שחיטה. shechita. Okay, so now let's continue in
the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, משנה לא זזה ממקומה. mishna lo zaz mi'mekomah.
גופא. gufa.
So let's go back and look at this question, this statement of
ריש לקיש Resh Lakish that when an organ is injured in the
middle of שחיטה. shechita. אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Resh Lakish, excuse me,
next line, גופא. gufa. אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Resh Lakish, שחט את
הקנה ואחר כך ניקבה הריאה, shachat et ha'kaneh ve'achar kach nikva ha'rei'ah,
you cut, you shechted the trachea and then there was a hole
in the lung.
אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so says רבא, Rava, לא אמר רבי שמעון
בן לקיש הכי, lo amar Rabi Shimon ben Lakish hachi, ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish
did not say this, אלא
בריאה, ela bereia, only with the lung, הואיל
וחיי ריאה תלויה בקנה ho'il ve'chayei reia teluya bakaneh
because the life of the lung is dependent on the trachea. So
once the trachea is cut, that whole unit is not there and
you cannot make it a טרפה treifah by having a hole in
the lung. אבל בבני מעיים, aval bivnei mei'ayim, if you got a
hole in any of the other internal organs, לא, lo, it could
become a טרפה. treifah. So as long as the animal is not
finished being שחוט, shachut, interestingly it might have made this dependent on
the question whether שחיטה shechita is the whole process or only the
end, but as long as the animal's not fully שחוטה, shechuta, it
can still become a טרפה treifah even in the middle of the
process. As long as it's in an organ that has not, you
know, has not already effectively been rendered moot by the שחיטה. shechita.
So if it's a hole in the lung or let's say you
start by cutting the esophagus, presumably, and then you got a hole
in the stomach, you know, then presumably that would be irrelevant. You've
already cut that and that's part of the act of שחיטה. shechita.
But if it's got a טרפה treifah in some other unrelated organ,
according to this, it would become a טרפה. treifah. Okay now that
is though not agreed upon. Why?
Because מתקיף לה רבי זירא, matkif lah Rabi Zeira, excuse me one
second, make sure I realize something. So רבי זירא Rabi Zeira asked
on this. So מתקיף לה רבי זירא, matkif lah Rabi Zeira, מאחר
שנודע בו סימני טרפה, me'acher shenoda bo simanei treifah, התרתה, hityarta, once
it had a טרפה, treifah, a thing, you know, סימני טרפה simanei
treifah means a sign of טרפה, treifah, meaning, you know, a indication
or a phenomenon of טרפה. treifah. Once it had one of these
phenomena, phenomenon, התרתה hityarta and you said it was permissible, מה לי
ריאה מה לי בני מעיים, ma li reia ma li bnei mei'ayim,
it shouldn't matter if it's on lung or any other organ. Meaning
he says, I understand your logic to say once the שחיטה shechita
act has begun, you can no longer make it a טרפה. treifah.
You're in the process of killing it. Don't talk to me about
whether it's still vital or not. Okay, once the process has begun,
you can no longer make it a טרפה. treifah. But then don't
distinguish between the lungs and the other organs. I would not, you
know, I'm not going to, once I'm going to look at what
your שחיטה shechita is doing, I'm not going to focus so micro
and say oh it ruined, you've already destroyed the trachea, lung, that's
not relevant. If because I'm looking at what your שחיטה shechita is
doing, I'm saying you're in the middle of killing it, don't talk
to me about טרפות treifos anymore. So he says according to it,
it should not matter where that damage occurred once the act has
begun.
Could you have said that even before then? I mean.
No, then it's a נבילה. neveilah. You have to שחט shachat a
live vital animal, right? That's that's the whole point. So but once.
So you haven't finished shechting a live vital.
That's what he says. That if so he says, I I will
once you're saying that a damage to the lungs won't render it
a problem in the middle, a damage to any organ won't render,
once you're in the process of killing it, it you cannot start
talking to me about whether it's still vital or not. Okay, I
mean yes you could understand saying only the lungs, but you could
also understand saying once you begin it shouldn't matter. Okay, and that's
what he says.
Okay, that's not the case here because you're supposed to finish if
you stop after you did one סימן siman and you're looking to
see if there's a.
No, because you can always check the the organs afterwards, right? Okay.
So okay. So he says, so he says I it shouldn't matter.
וחזר בו רבי זירא. vachazar bo Rabi Zeira. But רבי זירא Rabi
Zeira reversed himself. Now there's a whole question if he reversed the
first statement or he reversed himself from the second statement we're about
to see. It's a debate of רש"י תוספות. Rashi Tosafot. I'm going
to read it like רש"י. Rashi. He reversed his first claim that
it never makes it a טרפה treifah based on the following statement.
דבעי רבי זירא, de'ba'ei Rabi Zeira, because רבי זירא Rabi Zeira asked
the following question. ניקבו בני מעיים בין סימן לסימן מהו. nikvu bnei
mei'ayim bein siman lesiman mahu. Let's say again, the internal organs got
a hole in them, which would make it a טרפה treifah between
the trachea and the esophagus, between the two סימנים. simanim. What is
the law? Now we're going to see that he's going to assume
within this question that the animal will certainly be a טרפה treifah
because it got a hole in an internal organ before the שחיטה
shechita was done even though between the two סימנים. simanim. So that's
how we see he reversed himself, because the assumption of this question
is that the animal was definitely a טרפה. treifah. Okay, as opposed
to what he said before that once the שחיטה shechita act starts
it can't be a טרפה. treifah. What then is his question? His
question is maybe it should be worse than a טרפה. treifah. Maybe
it should be a נבילה. neveilah. Why? Because think about what you're
doing. You're שוחט, shochet, you cut the trachea. That act of שחיטה
shechita was going to make this animal kosher and מותר mutar to
eat. Then then there became a hole in the, I don't know,
stomach or the heart. Now it's a טרפה. treifah. Okay, that we're
assuming. Now you're going to finish שחיטה. shechta. What's the purpose of
the finishing of the shechting? It's no longer this an act of
שחיטה shechita that's going to make it permissible to eat, it's already
a טרפה. treifah. The only thing the act of שחיטה shechita can
do once an animal is a טרפה treifah is make it not
a נבילה. neveilah. Make it that, you know, it doesn't communicate טומאה.
tumah. טרפה Treifah and נבילה neveilah it's going to be forbidden to
eat. The only difference is that if it's a טרפה, treifah, if
you did a good שחיטה shechita but there's an injury, it's not
a נבילה, neveilah, it's not טמא. tamei. So the first half of
the act was going to make it permissible. The second half of
the act was only going to make it a non נבילה. neveilah.
So he says maybe those two halves of the act because they
have different functions should not combine to make one unified act. And
if they don't combine. you never did a שחיטה shechita and the
animal actually is a נבילה. neveila. Okay, that's his question. Neither do
I. But okay. The point is, is that each one serves a
different halachic function. The beginning of the act serves the function of
שחיטה shechita to make it permissible to eat, the second half of
the act when it became a טריפה treifa only is a שחיטה
shechita to make it a non-נבילה. neveila. Since then, now there is
an overlap because the first half also would have made it a
non-נבילה. neveila. So it is true, one is a subset of the
other, but because they're not the exact same halachic purpose, maybe we
can't call it one halachic act. And therefore we can't call it
a שחיטה shechita and the animal's a נבילה. neveila. That's his question.
What interests us is his assumption that it definitely is a טריפה
treifa once it got an injury between the two סימנים. simanim. So
let's just read that. מהו, mahu, what's the law? מי מצטרף סימן
ראשון לסימן שני mi mitztaref siman rishon l'siman sheini does the cutting
of the first סימן siman combined with the cutting of the second
סימן siman לטהרה מידי נבילה l'tahara midei neveila to at least say
it's a good שחיטה shechita and the animal isn't a נבילה? neveila?
Yes, it's a טריפה, treifa, it got this hole, but at least
it's not a נבילה, neveila, at least you did a שחיטה shechita
on it. או לא, o lo, or do we say no, since
the two halves had different functions, it wasn't even a שחיטה shechita
and therefore the animal is a נבילה. neveila. ואמרינן v'amrinan and we
responded לאו היינו דבעי אילפא, lav haynu d'ba'ei ilfa, that's pretty much
the same question אילפא Ilfa asked in this other case. הוציא עובר
ידו בין סימן לסימן, hotzi ubar yado bein siman l'siman, a fetus
was in the mother of a cow and it stuck out its
arm from the womb in the middle of the שחיטה. shechita. Now,
an interesting הלכה halacha is, is that if a fetus is in
the womb and the cow is shachted, the fetus is considered shachted.
The שחיטה shechita of the mother applies to the fetus. Even if
the fetus is then born alive and is walking around, it's considered
already shachted. However, based out of a פסוק pasuk which we'll see
when we get to this פרק, perek, it says that if the
fetus's arm is stuck out or any limb is stuck out when
it is shachted, that limb is considered a טריפה. treifa. I'm not
going to discuss why now, we'll worry about that
later, but that limb is a טריפה treifa if it stuck out
before the שחיטה. shechita. So now he says what if it stuck
out that limb between the two סימנים? simanim? Very similar. This limb
became a טריפה treifa in the middle. Okay, so now you're going
to, when you began the שחיטה, shechita, the שחיטה shechita would have
made that limb permissible. By the time you end the שחיטה, shechita,
that limb will not be permissible. At most, you know, it'll be
a טריפה treifa and not טמא. tamei. Even even if it stuck
back in? No, it didn't stick back in. We're not there. Okay.
So do the two halves combine in order to say it was
a good שחיטה shechita on the limb at least that it is
a טריפה treifa and not a נבילה? neveila? Exact same type of
a question. מהו, mahu, what do we say? מי אמרינן מי מצטרף
סימן ראשון, mi amrinan mi mitztaref siman rishon, דף ל"ג ע"א, daf
lamed gimmel amud aleph, מי מצטרף סימן ראשון לסימן שני לטהרה מידי
נבילה או לא? mi mitztaref siman rishon l'siman sheini l'tahara midei neveila
o lo?
Does the cutting of the first סימן siman combine with the cutting
of the second to say that that limb is not considered a
נבילה? neveila? At least it got a good שחיטה, shechita, even though
it's a טריפה. treifa. Okay, so those are questions about when either
a limb or the animal itself becomes a טריפה treifa between the
two סימנים. simanim. But what do you see? עד כאן לא איבעיא
לן אלא לטהרה מידי נבילה. ad kan lo ibayei lan ela l'tahara
midei neveila. You see that the whole question is, can you save
it from being a נבילה? neveila? אבל באכילה אסורה. aval b'achila asura.
But it clearly assumes that an injury between the two סימנים simanim
makes it a טריפה, treifa, makes it forbidden to be eaten. That
is the assumption of the question. The question is just now is
the whole שחיטה shechita lost. So again you see that רבי זירא
Rabbi Zeira reversed himself and said that an injury does make it
a, an injury in the middle does make it a טריפה. treifa.
אמר ליה רב אחא בר רב לרבינא, amar lei Rav Acha bar
Rav l'Ravina, רב אחא בר רב Rav Acha bar Rav said to
רבינא, Ravina, no, דילמא לעולם לא הדר ביה. dilma l'olam lo hadar
bei. Maybe he didn't reverse himself. דרבי זירא לדבריו דרבא קאמר. d'Rabbi
Zeira l'divrei d'Rava ka'amar. Maybe he's just responding according to רבא's Rava
own logic.
Okay. דליה לא סבירא ליה. d'lei lo sevira lei. He himself does
not hold of it. Meaning, maybe he is saying look, I hold
that any injury once you start the process does not make it
a טריפה. treifa. Right? You start killing it, it can't be a
טריפה treifa now. But according to you רבא, Rava, that you hold
that the only thing that gets saved is the lungs because they're
connected to the trachea, but other injuries can make it a טריפה,
treifa, then I want to ask you this interesting, you know, hypothetical
about, you know, will it save it from being a נבילה neveila
or not. Okay, so we don't know whether רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira
reversed himself, but here you have an interesting question which is can
an animal become a טריפה treifa in the middle of the process
of שחיטה shechita or not. Certainly the, the trachea or whatever sort
of, you know, system you've already destroyed, making it a טריפה treifa
is no longer relevant. But will it, can it becoming a טריפה
treifa in another part of the organs, will that make it a
טריפה treifa in the middle of the process? Okay, and that is
a question that is debated and is not resolved.
What do we say?
Well, it, I don't know. It's a good question. First of all,
it's not clear what רבי זירא's Rabbi Zeira position was itself. A,
the גמרא Gemara doesn't know if he's himself reversed himself and B,
רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot debate which side he was reversed to.
And we also don't know if we rule like him.
Right. So I don't know, I would have to check. Okay. So
anyway, okay. אמר רב פפא בר יצחק amar Rav Pappa bar Yitzchak
שמע מינה מדרבי שמעון בן לקיש. shma mina mi'de'Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish.
Now we're going to shift into a nice little different conversation that
we've touched on before, which is the difference between Jews and non-Jews
and that by Jews that there's a concept of... Now we're going
to shift into a nice little different conversation that we've touched on
before, which is the difference between Jews and non-Jews and that by
Jews that there's a concept of שחיטה, shechita, there was שחיטה, shechita,
so the animal doesn't have to be dead technically, it just has
to be שחוטה, shechuta, whereas for non-Jews there's not a concept of
שחיטה, shechita, there is a concept of אבר מן החי, eiver min
hachai, limb while the animal is still alive, so from that perspective
the animal actually has to be dead. So let's take a look.
שמע מינה מדרבי שמעון בן לקיש, Shma mina mi-de-Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish,
we see from Shimon Lakish's idea that once you've shechted the trachea,
even before you've finished, that it's like that whole system, the trachea
and the lungs, are already, you know, removed. We can infer from
that this the following: מזמנין ישראל אבני מעיים, Mazminin Yisrael a-benei me'ayim,
if you want to eat the inner organs of an animal after
you've shechted it, right? And for some people that was a whole
delicacy. What do they have? What, what? I don't know, פאשא pasha
or something or sweetbreads or, right.
For some they ate a lot of.
Yeah, all those inner organs are considered real delicacies. So you can
invite your Jewish friends to eat from the inner organs, ואין מזמנין
עובדי כוכבים אבני מעיים, ve-ein mazminin ovdei kochavim a-benei me'ayim,
but you can't invite non-Jews. Why not? מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, what's
the reason? ישראל דבשחיטה תליא מילתא, Yisrael de-vi-shechita talya milta, by a
Yisrael that it's about shechita, so כיון דאיכא שחיטה מעליא היא, keivan
de-ika shechita malya hi, שריא להו. sharya lehu.
Since there was a good shechita, it's permitted. Okay, but it's also
dead, so let's keep on going. עובדי כוכבים דבנחירה סגיא להו, Ovdei
kochavim de-ve-nechira sagya lehu, a
non-Jew that they can even, you know, kill it without shechting it,
just like stab it or something, so there's no concept of shechita,
ובמיתה תליא מילתא, u-ve-mita talya milta,
it's about death, so הני כאבר מן החי דמו. hani ke-eiver min
hachai damu.
These organs, inner organs, are like eiver min hachai
in a case where you've only shechted.
No. So what does that mean? I mean, the animal did die,
why is it eiver min hachai? So this is very bizarre. Remember
the Gemara's phrase before, which it said why by Reish Lakish does
a hole in the lung not matter after you cut the trachea?
Because it's like the whole thing is in a basket. Once you
cut the trachea, that whole system is already, you know, as if
it were removed, is no longer relevant. So the Gemara takes the
'as if' extremely literally for some strange reason and says, oh, so
if you cut the trachea before you finish shechita and certainly before
the animal died, it's like that whole system is removed. That's the
way we save it from being considered a טריפה treifa when it
gets a hole in the lung. So if that's removed, imagine that
you actually cut the trachea, imagine as if you actually then pulled
out the trachea and the lung. Let's imagine that. And then you
finished shechting. Okay, what would be the status? Well, for a non-Jew,
the animal wasn't dead when you removed the lung, so the lung
is an אבר מן החי. eiver min hachai. For a Jew, even
though the animal wasn't dead, it was in the process of being
shechted and that lung was removed because of an act of שחיטה,
shechita, so therefore that lung actually would be permissible once the shechita
has finished. So it is a very so the reason I can't
invite the non-Jew to have my organs is because if I'm going
to serve lung or if I'm going to serve stomach or something
like that, and that was so when I cut that סימן siman
before I finished the other סימן, siman, it was like it was
already removed while the animal was still alive because שחיטה's shechita not
a meaningful process, and therefore it's אבר מן
החי.
eiver
min hachai. Very bizarre. First of all, it depends which one, but
forget the it depends which one, it's completely bizarre that I would
consider it אבר מן החי eiver min hachai if it was in
the process of being killed and it wasn't physically removed. It might
be as if, so that the hole isn't relevant, but it is
very bizarre that the Gemara takes that as if so literally and
really treats it as אבר מן החי eiver min hachai for a
non-Jew. Anyway, now we're going to get onto the next stage, which
is how can you have something forbidden while no, let's see how
it finishes. Can you have something that's forbidden for a non-Jew and
permissible for a Jew? Now the more relevant example of this is
not this 'as if' it were removed. The more relevant example is
where you literally removed it. You shechted not and also not in
the middle of שחיטה, shechita, right? You shechted an animal, it's still
alive, walking around, it hasn't died yet, but it's shechted, and then
you ripped off a piece of meat. So for a Jew, it's
a shechted animal, it's not אבר מן החי eiver min hachai yet.
For a non-Jew, it's still alive, it's אבר מן החי. eiver min
hachai. So the more relevant example where it's forbidden for a non-Jew
and permissible for a Jew is when you fully
shechted it and then you removed something. But this Gemara's teaching this
idea as if it's been removed very literally. So let's see how
this discussion finishes. Okay, אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Pappa, so Rav
Pappa said, הוינא יתבינא קמיה דרב אחא בר יעקב, havina yatvina kameih
de-Rav Acha bar Yaakov, I was sitting in front of Rav Acha
bar Yaakov when he told over this ruling, ובעי דאימא ליה, u-ve'ei
de-eima leih, and I wanted to say to him the following question:
מי איכא מידי דלישראל שרי ולעובד כוכבים אסור? mi ika midi de-le-Yisrael
shari u-le-ovad kochavim assur?
How could that be? Does there ever exist anything that is permissible
to a Jew and forbidden to a non-Jew? This is a principle
that the Gemara has in סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, which gets violated a good
number of times, which I'll talk about in a minute, but at
least it's a principle that we supposedly try to hold by, that,
you know, the idea of the מצוות mitzvot that the Jews were
given are added to the prohibitions of the בני נח, Bnei Noach,
of the non-Jews. So how can there ever exist something that is
permissible to a Jew and forbidden to a non-Jew? I mean one
way of framing this is, A, in terms of the מצוות mitzvot
we got, that the מצוות mitzvot were just added to the pre-existing
מצוות. mitzvot. The other more interesting way of framing this is, it's
also the question about identity. We are not only Jews, we're also
part of the human... and as part of the human race, we
have the שבע מצוות בני נח. sheva mitzvos b'nei noach. Okay? That
is maybe a more startling way of framing it, but regardless, the
גמרא gemara says it can't be something that is permissible to Jews
and forbidden to non-Jews. So how can you say that these organs,
you know, the lung or whatever are forbidden to non-Jews and permissible
to Jews?
You know, when you convert you can marry your sister.
Okay, so we'll talk about those things. So anyway, so I wanted
to ask him that question, ולא אמרי ליה, v'lo amri lei, but
I didn't ask him that question. Why not? דאמינא de-amina because I,
you know, I said to myself, האי טעמא קאמר, hai ta'ama ka'amar,
he's giving a good reason why there's a difference. So maybe like
in principle, things are not more permissible to Jews than to non-Jews,
but there could be a technical reason why, because there's a concept
of שחיטה shechita by Jews, there's not a concept of שחיטה shechita
by non-Jews, and that leads to this difference of when something is
שחט shechted and not yet dead. So it's a consequence of actually
a stringency. The stringency is that Jews require שחיטה shechita and the
meat is forbidden without שחיטה. shechita. A consequence of that is that
there could be a certain leniency that derives when the animal is
שחט shechted and not yet dead. So I didn't ask him the
question. But it seems like the question has not fully been tabled
because now we're going to say that there are those that disagree.
תניא דלא כרב אחא בר יעקב. Tanya d'lo k'Rav Acha bar Yaakov.
הרוצה לאכול מבהמה קודם שתצא נפשה. Harotze leechol mib'hema kodem she'teitzei nafsha.
If somebody wants to eat from the meat of an animal before
it dies. Now, meaning that you want the meat ripped from the
animal before the animal has died. Apparently, that we're going to see
is considered to be, you know, we're not seeing but the גמרא
gemara somewhere else says that that actually has some health benefits to
it. So what can you do?
חודך כזית בשר מבית השחיטה, Chodech kezayis basar mibeis hashechita, you cut
away a כזית kezayis of meat, it doesn't matter how much, it's
just meat, from the place of the שחיטה. shechita. Meaning from exactly,
you שחט shechted it. It's still alive, part, good thing, whatever, some
other people if they were here would give you a very hard
time about צער בעלי חיים, tzaar baalei chayim, which as I've told
you is not something that's played out in these גמרות. gemaros. Anyway,
you שחט shechted it, it's still alive, you want to get some
meat right now. The easiest way to grab meat is from the
place where you've already cut, there the neck, the meat is exposed
and you don't have to start flaying the skin. So there it
is, it's still alive, you rip out a piece of meat from
the neck before the animal is dead, okay, that's מבית השחיטה. mibeis
hashechita. ומולחו יפה יפה, Umolcho yafe yafe, you do מליחה melicha well
to get out the blood, okay? ומדיחו יפה יפה, Umedicho yafe yafe,
you rinse it to remove the surface
blood. וממתין לו עד שתצא נפשה. Umamtin lo ad she'teitzei nafsha. Now,
it is true you have to wait for the animal to die.
Why? Now you ripped it off while the animal was alive. So
the big חידוש chiddush is that it's not אבר מן החי. ever
min hachai. Since the animal was שחט, shechted, although it's still alive,
it's not אבר מן החי. ever min hachai. That's what we said.
Why do you wait for the animal to die? רש"י Rashi says
oh, there's another idea that the Rabbis learned, חז"ל Chazal learned from
the verse, לא תאכלו על הדם, lo sochlu al hadam, don't eat
from the meat while the animal is still alive. So it's not
אבר מן החי, ever min hachai, but at least we do have
that sensibility or that prohibition that says don't eat while the animal
is still living. But although since it was removed when it was
שחט, shechted, it is technically not אבר מן החי. ever min hachai.
And therefore, as soon as it dies, ואוכלו, v'ochlo, you can eat
it. So you don't have to wait so you still get it
when it has a lot of that life force still in
it. Okay, very nice. That is the principle of number one, ignoring
צער בעלי חיים, tzaar baalei chayim, and number two, the principle that
after שחיטה shechita it's permissible, it's not אבר מן החי ever min
hachai even if still alive. But now look at the next line.
אחד עובדי כוכבים ואחד ישראל מותרים בו, Echad ovdei kochavim v'echad Yisrael
mutarim bo, whether a non-Jew and Jews are permitted. So this clearly
goes against רב אחא בר יעקב, Rav Acha bar Yaakov, because this
says that by non-Jews, even though we assumed there's not a concept
of שחיטה, shechita, once it is permissible to a Jew because of
שחיטה, shechita, it's also not אבר מן החי ever min hachai for
a non-Jew. And presumably this is on the principle that you don't
have something that is more permissible to a Jew than to a
non-Jew. But the interesting thing is, if I told you this, if
I said, okay, here's a case where logic would dictate it's permissible
to a Jew but forbidden to a non-Jew. I'm sorry, the opposite,
yeah. No, it's permissible to a Jew, forbidden to a non-Jew. But
we have a principle, something can't be more permissible to Jews than
non-Jews. How am I going to fix this problem? What would you
say I should do? It was permissible to a Jew, forbidden to
a non-Jew, but I can't make it more permissible to Jews than
non-Jews, so what should I say?
You could say it's forbidden for everybody.
Presumably I would be strict and I'd say, okay, then I have
to assume it's also forbidden to Jews. If it's forbidden to non-Jews,
it should be forbidden to Jews. This did the reverse. It said
if the תורה Torah introduces a concept of שחיטה, shechita, which means
that it's no longer אבר מן החי ever min hachai and you
can eat it even when the animal was removed when the animal
was still alive, if that's true for Jews and it's permissible to
Jews, it's got to also be true for non-Jews. That's very bizarre.
When the גמרא gemara normally attends to this principle, it makes it
forbidden for both, not permissible for both. But that's what he says.
Okay, it's permissible for both. So now the גמרא gemara says, מסייע
ליה לרב אידי בר אבין, mesayei lei l'Rav Idi bar Avin, דאמר
רב אידי בר אבין אמר רב יצחק בר אשיאן, d'amar Rav Idi
bar Avin amar Rav Yitzchak bar Ashian, הרוצה שיברי. harotze she'yavri.
And here's the health benefit, if you want to get strong, so
forget steroids or exercise, חודך כזית בשר בבית שחיטה. chodech kezayis basar
b'beis shechita. בהמה, behemah, cut out a כזית kezayit of meat when
the, from the place where you שחט shechted the animal while it's
still alive and it's got that life force in it, ומולחו יפה
יפה ומדיחו יפה יפה, u-molcho yafe yafe u-medicho yafe yafe, first of
all salt it and rinse it, get out the blood, וממתין לה
עד שתצא נשמתה, u-mamtin lah ad she-teitzei nishmatah, you do have to
wait for the animal to die, not because of אבר מן החי
ever min ha-chai but because of another problem, אחד עובדי כוכבים ואחד
ישראל מותר באלו, echad ovdei kochavim ve-echad Yisrael mutar be-eilu, and once
again Jews and non-Jews. So here we go that number one that,
A, it attends to the principle of nothing can be permissible to
Jews forbidden to non-Jews, and bizarrely it therefore says it's going to
be permissible to non-Jews. Now this תוספות Tosafot here you know tries
to work this out because there are times where we say things
are forbidden for Jews and permissible to non-Jews. I'll give you a
great very contemporary example which leads to a lot of interesting public
policy discussion, right? There's a whole question about what הלכה halacha says
about abortion. Is abortion you know permissible, is it forbidden, if it
is forbidden how bad is it forbidden, is it considered murder, is
it considered injury, what's the nature of the permit, etc. All of
that is discussions with Jews, but actually the גמרא Gemara is explicit
that of the שבע מצות בני נח sheva mitzvot bnei Noach of
murder for non-Jews is included the, the, you know, the killing of
a fetus. That that is considered murder for non-Jews. Okay, that גמרא
Gemara in סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, I forget the דף, daf, ע"ג Ayin Gimmel
or something like that. Anyway, part of the reason might be, and
this is another issue that תוספות Tosafot discusses, is that the גמרא
Gemara doesn't have a concept of שיעורים shiurim for, for non-Jews, meaning
for a Jew for example you don't transgress until you eat a
כזית. kezayit. You don't transgress until you steal a, you know, פרוטה
perutah worth. For a non-Jew there's no sense of no minimum, there's
never no minimum שיעורים. shiurim. You, if you eat אבר מן החי
ever min ha-chai even the smallest amount, if you steal even the
smallest amount. So the same could be about murder, how do you
define life? There's no minimum definition. So whatever the case might be,
it is more forbidden for non-Jews than it is for Jews. For
non-Jews it really is murder. So that, these types of issues תוספות
Tosafot deals with. Sometimes there's ways out of it by saying okay
it's still forbidden for Jews, it's not as bad, but to eat
a half a כזית kezayit of חזיר, chazir, to steal less than
a פרוטה, perutah, to abort a fetus is still forbidden, it might
not be murder, it might not be as bad, but it's still
forbidden. But other times the point is this principle doesn't always apply,
like the גמרא Gemara said, I didn't ask him because he said
a reason, meaning in general there's nothing that's more forbidden for Jews
than for non-Jews, but sometimes it's a logical derivation of a, of
certain differences and it does play out to translate into a difference.
So תוספות Tosafot tries to work it out, but you know this
is an interesting battleground here for this general question of do we
always, you know, does this principle always hold or not? And again
what's fascinating about this גמרא Gemara is the last opinion that assumes
it does hold, applied it to be lenient rather than to be
strict, which is quite unexpected.
Now we turn, what, do you have a, you know, reason why
it would choose to do that here as opposed to...?
No, I don't. It's very strange. Normally we assume it the other
way, we assume because of this principle we have to assume it's
forbidden for Jews. Okay, so now we go on and this next
משנה Mishnah now I do have to warn you, it's forbidden? Yeah,
well, I don't know how we rule. I shouldn't have asked such
a hard question. Yeah, I know. So I'm sorry, I did not
prepare, didn't prepare for the answer. Okay. Now we go on, now
this next משנה, Mishnah, I have to warn you for the remainder
of today and the next two days, we're going to shift gear
and be talking about a lot of טומאה וטהרה tumah ve-taharah because
of the focus of this משנה. Mishnah. So do not say you
were not warned. Okay. So here is the משנה. Mishnah. השוחט בהמה
חיה ועוף, ha-shochet behemah chayah va-of, if somebody slaughters whatever it might
be,
you know, cattle, a deer, a bird, ולא יצא מהן דם. ve-lo
yatza meihen dam.
Remember we said that you don't have to cut the, the blood
vessels, even according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda we said it was
only for birds, but certainly for the רבנן Rabbanan you don't have
to cut the blood vessels. So you managed to do a very
precise שחיטה, shechita, you severed the trachea and the esophagus and you
did not cut any blood vessels. Certainly not enough that, that any
blood came, whatever, no blood came out. So כשרים, ksherim, it's kosher
because you don't obviously שחיטה shechita doesn't require that, or not obviously,
but it's still kosher.
Only if you say דם dam there is דם, dam, right?
You only need כיסוי הדם kisuy ha-dam if there is דם. dam.
ונאכלין בידיים מסואבות, ve-ne-echalin be-yadayim mesuo-avot, and you can eat them with
dirty hands. Now literally that's dirty hands, but here מסואבות mesuo-avot technically
means טמא tamei hands. Because remember food only becomes susceptible to becoming
טמא tamei if it comes in contact with water or liquid. One
of the liquids is blood. Okay, but here you have food, meat,
that did not come in contact with liquid and therefore you can
eat them with hands that are טמא, tamei, you won't make it
טמא. tamei. Now תוספות Tosafot of course says what about, I don't
understand תוספות Tosafot says, in order to get the blood out you
have to salt it and rinse it. So you're going to get
water on it. So what?
And there's some moisture in flesh even if it's...
That's a good point but that's not considered to be the halachic
definition of, of liquids is, you know, water, blood, honey, you know,
dew, which is water. Anyway, you know, anyway there's certainly wine. So
yes, we could say that this is H2O content, you know, but
the גמרא Gemara does not acknowledge, recognize that as water. Okay, but,
but anyway, so תוספות Tosafot says well, you know, could be for
example you roast
it... Okay, so here you have this meat that has not come
in contact with blood, I mean with fresh blood that came out
of the animal other than its internal blood. So therefore it is
not susceptible and you can eat it with טמא tamei hands. לפי
שלא הוכשרו בדם Lefi shelo huchshru b'dam because they did not become
susceptible to becoming טמא tamei through the blood. רבי שמעון אומר הוכשרו
בשחיטה. Rebbi Shimon omer huchshru b'shchita. Rebbi Shimon says I know that
is true, but since the act of שחיטה shchita turned it into
food, this very thing that turned it into food enough makes it
considered food that can become טמא. tamei. If you have something like
a fruit that is growing that is naturally food, you could say
it is not טמא tamei until somehow it comes under human control.
This is actually this other interesting point I would say parallel to
our discussion we had about vessels, that things have to almost be
like human artifacts to become טמא. tamei. So food, one of the
way of understanding why it needs to come in contact with liquid—and
remember you have to want it to come into contact with liquid—might
have to be to take it from its natural state to somehow
under human control, so you rinse it, you want it to come
in contact with liquid, the desire. So he is saying okay, that
is by things that just are completely natural, here you did an
act and made it food, you שחט shechted it. In that case
you do not need the contact of liquid in order to make
it fit to become טמא. tamei.
So this is only by חולין chulin anyway, right?
Right. And that is the first thing the גמרא Gemara is going
to say. So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. טעמא
דלא יצא מהן דם, Taama d'lo yatza meihen dam, so the reason
that it's not a problem is because no blood came out. הא
יצא מהן דם, Ha yatza meihen dam, if blood did come out,
אין נאכלין בידיים מסואבות, ein ne'echalin b'yadayim mesovos, they cannot be eaten
with טמא tamei hands. אמאי, Amai, why is that true? ידים שניות
הן, Yadayim shnios hen, your hands are—the reason we wash our hands
before bread is because the Rabbis said they made a גזירה, gezeira,
you never know what your hands are touching, so we have to
assume your hands are טמא, tamei, we're going to treat them as
though they're טמא tamei level two. Now what does טומאה tumah level
two do? It makes something into a three but not anything, only
תרומה, trumah, only תרומה trumah or קדשים kodshim it can make into
a three. Normal חולין chulin it cannot affect. So the reason we
wash our hands is because כהנים Kohanim would have to wash their
hands before they ate תרומה, trumah, classic תרומה trumah would be flour
bread because it would be from the grain products. So therefore to
remember what the כהנים Kohanim would do with their תרומה trumah based
on this rabbinic idea of making the hands into a שני, sheini,
we wash our hands before eating bread. Okay, that is the גמרא
Gemara is not saying that but a quick little lesson about the
relevance of this. So the hands are considered a שני. sheini. So
now your hands are a שני, sheini, therefore what? ידים שניות הן
ואין שני עושה שלישי בחולין. Yadayim shnios hen v'ein sheini oseh shlishi
b'chulin. So since this is not sacrifices, even if the meat were
susceptible for being טמא, tamei, who cares?
Let your hands touch it, your hands are a שני, sheini, they
have no impact on stuff that is non-sanctified. So who cares? Let
it be susceptible, it's still not going to be a problem.
וממאי דבחולין עסקינן, U'mimai d'v'chulin askinan, who told you we're talking about
חולין? chulin? Maybe although it's מסכת חולין, Masechet Chulin, all of a
sudden we're talking about sacrifices. So the גמרא Gemara has like five
answers to prove that we're talking about חולין. chulin. This could be
a little experiment. How many proofs can you find from this משנה
Mishnah we're talking about חולין? chulin? Almost? Give me two Michael.
One of them is first of all you need to do זריקת
הדם zerikas hadam with a קרבן. korban.
Ah, how could you say no blood? You need blood for a
קרבן. korban. And give me one other answer.
And then—and then
the—what was I thinking? No I just
had it.
Ah, you're going to be surprised at this one, let's take a
look.
No, no, no, yeah, חיבת הקדש. chibbas hakodesh.
Ah, okay good, those are three answers. That was more obscure.
You're right. The גמרא Gemara is going to say a first very
straightforward one, וממאי דבחולין עסקינן, u'mimai d'v'chulin askinan, how do you know
we're talking about חולין? chulin? דקתני חיה, De-katani chaya, because it says
a חיה. chaya. You never have a deer or a חיה chaya
that's a קרבן. korban. דאילו קדשים חיה בקדשים מי איכא? De-ilu kodshim
chaya b'kodshim mi ika? You never have a חיה chaya that's a
קרבן. korban.
ותו, V'tu, alright,
ותו, v'tu, doesn't matter, it's a question anyway. ותו אי בקדשים, V'tu
e' b'kodshim, if it's sacrifices, כי לא יצא מהן דם כשרה? ki
lo yatza meihen dam kesheira? How could you say with no blood
it's good? הוא עצמו לדם הוא צריך, Hu atzmo l'dam hu tzarich,
you need the blood for a קרבן, korban, the whole purpose of
a קרבן korban of שחיטה shechting is to get the blood, you
can't do the קרבן korban without the blood. ותו, V'tu, and in
addition number three, אי בקדשים, e' b'kodshim, if it is קדשים, kodshim,
כי יצא מהן דם מי מכשיר? ki yatza meihen dam mi machshir?
Blood of קדשים, kodshim, interestingly, does not make food susceptible for טומאה.
tumah. If you have a blood of sacrifice that touches a fruit
or something, it does not make it susceptible for טומאה. tumah. Why
not? ואמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן מנין לדם קדשים
שאינו מכשיר, V'amar Rebbi Chiya bar Abba amar Rebbi Yochanan minayin l'dam
kodshim she'eino machshir, how do we know blood of sacrifices does not
make food susceptible? משנאמר, Mi-shene'emar, the verse says: על הארץ תשפכנו כמים,
Al ha'aretz tishpachenu kamayim, when it talks about slaughtering animals outside of
the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, spill it like water. דם שנשפך כמים
מכשיר, Dam shenishpach kamayim machshir,
blood that is spilled like water, meaning that you don't have to
catch it, right? The blood of sacrifice the whole idea is to
catch it, not to just let it spill. So blood that you
can let spill like water, that functions like water and it makes
a food susceptible for טומאה. tumah. דם שאינו נשפך כמים, Dam she'eino
nishpach kamayim,
if it's not let flowed spilled like water, you have to catch
it, אינו מכשיר, eino machshir, it does not make it susceptible. use
it as a sacrifice in the sacrificial act, אינו מכשיר eino machshir
does not function like water and cannot make things susceptible. So the
blood would not make the meat susceptible because blood of sacrifices doesn't
have that power. That's reason number three.
And the two and reason number four like Michael said, אי בקדשים
e'bkodeshim if it was sacrifices, כי לא יצא מהם דם לא מתכשרי,
ki lo yatza mehem dam, lo mitkashrei, you're telling me without blood
they're not susceptible? מתכשרי בחיבת הקודש. mitkashrei b'chibas hakodesh.
Let the dearness of the sanctity make them susceptible. וקיימא לן v'kayma
lan we have a principle: חיבת הקודש מכשירתן, chibas hakodesh machshartan,
things that are used in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, even things
like wood and frankincense, because they are things that are offered on
the, you know, their dearness of the sanctity in a sense makes
them more susceptible. So clearly we're not talking about sacrifices, we're talking
about חולין. chulin. And once we're talking about חולין chulin our big
question is why do I care if they became susceptible or not?
Even if they were susceptible, your hands which are שני sheini cannot
make חולין chulin a problem. חולין chulin cannot become a שלישי, shlishi,
because these people eat טהרה. taharah.
So we'll eventually get to that, but let's take a look. So
אמר רבי נחמן, Amar Rebbi Nachman, so that's the question we're going
to focus on for the next day or so. אמר רבי נחמן
אמר רבה בר אבוה: Amar Rebbi Nachman amar Rabah bar Avuha: הכא
בחולין שנלקחו בכסף מעשר עסקינן, Hacha b'chulin she'nelkachu b'chessef ma'aser askinan, ודלא
כרבי מאיר. v'dlo k'Rebbi Meir.
So the first answer is it is חולין, chulin, but it's חולין
chulin that you purchased with your מעשר שני ma'aser sheini money. Now,
because you purchased it with your מעשר שני ma'aser sheini money, it
has the sanctity of מעשר שני. ma'aser sheini. Now here's an interesting
question: we know that תרומה, trumah, right, which is very sanctified, right,
if a non כהן kohen eats תרומה trumah he's חייב מיתה chayav
misah and all these laws and so on, so that is we
know that can become a third-level טמא. tamei. חולין chulin cannot. How
about something like מעשר שני, ma'aser sheini, which is midpoint between תרומה
trumah and חולין? chulin? It's sanctified, but not sanctified to the point
that it excludes non כהנים. kohanim. It's just sanctified to the point
that you eat it in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Can that become a שלישי
shlishi or not? So here it's saying we are talking about meat
that was bought with מעשר שני ma'aser sheini money and we will
assume it can become a שלישי, shlishi, not like רבי מאיר. Rebbi
Meir. דתניא, D'tniya, because we learned in a משנה Mishnah that there
is a debate whether מעשר שני ma'aser sheini can become a third-level
טומאה tumah or not. כל הטעון ביאת מים מדברי סופרים, Kol hatone
bi'as mayim midivrei sofrim, anything that has to go in the water
rabbinically, meaning any type of rabbinic טומאה, tumah, okay, מטמא את הקודש,
metamei es hakodesh, meaning so standard rabbinic טומאה tumah is makes things
a שני. sheini. There are different ways rabbis made general rabbinic טומאות.
tumas. One is your hands are considered a שני, sheini, that we
said. That was a general thing that כהנים kohanim had to always
wash their hands before they ate תרומה. trumah. Another thing they said,
for example, is that if you eat טמא tamei food, you become
טמא. tamei. Now that is also rabbinic because biblically a person can
only become a ראשון. rishon. So if I eat טמא tamei food
and the food is a ראשון rishon because it touched let's say,
I don't know, a נבילה neveilah or something, then the food can
only make something a שני. sheini. The only thing that really can
become a שלישי shlishi is other food. So but the rabbi said
if I eat טמא tamei food, even though if I touch it
I'm nothing because again, a person can't become a שלישי shlishi according
to the Torah, if I eat it then I do become טמא
tamei and I become a שני. sheini. So the general principle is...
why that? Because they were concerned that while I'm eating this food
I'll also drink some תרומה trumah or something and the food will
touch the תרומה trumah liquid, whatever concerns they had. So therefore the
rabbi, therefore what you have is a series which we're not going
to talk about all of them, but a series of rabbinic טומאות
tumas where the consistent rule is that when the rabbis created a
טומאה tumah they made you a שני. sheini. So either if you
ate טמא tamei food they made you a שני, sheini, if your
hands are considered טמא tamei and you haven't washed them, they're a
שני, sheini, that's the rule. Rabbinic טומאה tumah is a שני, sheini,
second-degree derivative.
So let's read that again. כל הטעון ביאת מים, Kol hatone bi'as
mayim, anybody that has to go to the מקוה mikvah either your
whole body or washing your hands, מדברי סופרים midivrei sofrim based on
the rabbinic rule, מטמא את הקודש, metamei es hakodesh, so it is
a שני. sheini. What's the effect of a שני? sheini? It makes
sacrifices טמא, tamei, ופוסל את התרומה u'posel es hatrumah and invalidates תרומה
trumah because again, תרומה trumah can become a שלישי. shlishi. Why does
it use the word פוסל posel as opposed to מטמא? metamei? The
word מטמא metamei means that it can pass טומאה tumah on. So
if it touches a קרבן, korban, the קרבן korban becomes a שלישי
shlishi and it can make another קרבן korban a רביעי. revii. If
it touches תרומה, trumah, the תרומה trumah is a שלישי shlishi but
it ends there. If the תרומה trumah were to touch a קרבן
korban it would not pass it on. It ends there. Okay, but
the basic point is you are a שני, sheini, and so therefore
you don't touch sacrifices and תרומה, trumah, ומותר בחולין, u'mutar b'chulin, but
you can touch non-sanctified objects because חולין chulin cannot become a שלישי.
shlishi. ובמעשר, ub'ma'aser, and even with מעשר, ma'aser, meaning מעשר שני, ma'aser
sheini, דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rebbi Meir. That's what רבי מאיר Rebbi
Meir says. וחכמים אוסרים במעשר. vachachamim osrin b'ma'aser. The rabbis say no,
מעשר שני ma'aser sheini is like sanctified objects, it's like תרומה, trumah,
and therefore don't touch it, it'll become a שלישי. shlishi. So therefore
what are we saying? You're right, our משנה Mishnah is talking about,
is not talking about sacrifices. That we've proved. How do I know
by the way our משנה... Mishnah... so why don't we just say
our משנה Mishnah is talking about תרומה? trumah? So there's an obvious
answer. Why can our משנה Mishnah not be talking about תרומה? trumah?
Our משנה Mishnah
has all these things here, like חיה, chaya, or whatever, you don't
have תרומה. trumah. So is there something that's meat that can be
sanctified and not a sacrifice? And the answer is מעשר Maaser if
you purchased it with מעשר שני Maaser Sheni money. So that's what
we're saying, therefore it could be a שלישי, shlishi, and it's the
Rabbis who argue on רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir that say that מעשר
שני Maaser Sheni can become a שלישי. shlishi. Okay, so that's our
first answer. The גמרא's Gemara not going to be happy. מתקיף לה
רב שימי בר אשי. Matkif lah Rav Shimi bar Ashi. רב שימי
בר אשי Rav Shimi bar Ashi challenged this. ממאי, Mimai, who told
you that this is really what רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir and the
Rabbis debate? דילמא, Dilma, perhaps, עד כאן לא פליגי רבנן עליה דרבי
מאיר אלא באכילת מעשר, ad kan lo peligi rabanan alei d'Rebbi Meir
ela be'achilat Maaser, when did they say if you're טמא tamei there's
a problem with מעשר שני? Maaser Sheni? It means don't eat מעשר
שני. Maaser Sheni. אבל בנגיעה דמעשר, Aval bimegi'a d'Maaser, touching, just touching
מעשר, Maaser, ואכילה דחולין, ve'achila dechulin, and obviously eating חולין chulin which
everybody agrees wasn't a problem, לא פליגי, lo peligi, they would not
argue it. And that actually is not just a hypothetical, and actually
is the rule. Again, I'm not going to get into all of
the back story about this, but the same way I just told
you that if I touch טמא tamei food, I'm not טמא, tamei,
but if I eat it I am, so the Rabbis were stricter
in rabbinic טומאה tumah about eating things than touching them, it also
is true in the opposite direction. When we wanted to be strict
by מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni, okay, by תרומה, Truma, if I'm טמא
tamei and I touch even I touch תרומה Truma it's a problem.
But by מעשר שני Maaser Sheni which is more middle, you know,
sort of in the middle there, they said just don't eat it
if you're not if you're טמא. tamei. They didn't say don't touch
it. So therefore yes, the Rabbis say מעשר שני Maaser Sheni is
a problem, but it's only a problem by eating, it's not a
problem by touching. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says והא נגיעה היא,
veha negia hi, and our משנה Mishna that is saying you would
have a problem if the meat was susceptible is talking a problem
even about touching. How do I know our משנה Mishna is talking
about touching? Maybe our משנה Mishna is talking about eating. נאכלים Ne'echalin
sounds like it's talking about the problem of eating, not a problem
of touching. So the גמרא's Gemara going to make a very interesting,
you know, subtle inference that our משנה Mishna is talking about a
problem of touching. How do I know?
דקתני
נאכלים בידיים מסואבות. Dekatani ne'echalin beyadayim meso'avot. It is eaten with unclean
hands as opposed to you can eat it with unclean hands. So
נאכלים ne'echalin means somebody else can eat it. So what does it
mean? מי לא עסקינן, Mi lo askinan, are we not talking even
about a case דכספי ליה חבריה, dechasfi lei chavrei, that his friend
is feeding him? Meaning, so my hands are טמא, tamei, I take
this meat, and I am going to feed it to Michael. Michael
is טהור. tahor. Okay, so if I wanted to say that I
can eat it, I would say אוכלם בידיים מסואבות. ochlam beyadayim meso'avot.
Here I'm saying they can be fed or eaten by somebody else
and my hands are טמא. tamei. So the גמרא's Gemara choosing to
read the משנה, Mishna, it seems like a pretty subtle דיוק, diyuk,
but it's choosing to read the משנה Mishna that there's that if
the meat were a problem, were הוכשר, huchshar, were susceptible, I can't
even touch it. So don't give me some מעשר שני Maaser Sheni
answer. Even with מעשר שני Maaser Sheni is a problem if to
eat it if you're טמא, tamei, that's only about eating. Our משנה
Mishna suggests that there would be a problem even by touching if
it were susceptible. So we're back to our problem. Your hands are
שני, sheni, the meat is חולין, chulin, who cares if it's susceptible
or not? You cannot make חולין chulin meat or even מעשר שני
Maaser Sheni meat, you cannot make it טמא tamei by touching it
with a שני. sheni. So we're back to that question. So let's
take a look, another answer. אלא אמר רב פפא, Ella amar Rav
Pappa, רב פפא Rav Pappa says, הכא בידיים תחלות עסקינן. hacha biyadayim
techilot askinan. We're talking about hands that are תחלות, techilot, the beginning,
meaning that they are a ראשון. rishon. Okay, normal hands, the Rabbis
said normally you have to assume your hands are a שני. sheni.
But there are special cases where because of things your hands came
in contact with, your hands can be a ראשון. rishon. So it's
saying you're right, if your hands were normal hands as שני sheni
they couldn't affect חולין. chulin. We're talking about a special case that
your hands became a ראשון. rishon.
You had to touch a שרץ?
sheretz? Well, certainly if you really touched a שרץ sheretz then it
would be even biblical a ראשון. rishon. Moreover it wouldn't just be
your hands, so then it would be your whole body. So it
can't be. Only
biblical טומאה tumah is either all or nothing. Rabbinic טומאה tumah they
allowed to limit to just your hands. So it's going to have
to be rabbinic טומאה. tumah. We'll see in a second. But in
a case of rabbinic טומאה tumah where your hands are ראשון, rishon,
then they could make חולין chulin meat into a שני, sheni, and
that's what our משנה Mishna is talking about. Now what is that
case? Let's take a look. בידיים תחלות עסקינן. Biyadayim techilot askinan. רבי
שמעון בן אלעזר היא. Rebbi Shimon ben Elazar hi. It's רבי שמעון
בן אלעזר Rebbi Shimon ben Elazar that allows your hand that believes
there is a concept of your hands being a ראשון. rishon. דתניא,
Detanya,
אין ידיים תחלות לחולין. ein yadayim techilot lechulin. Your hands can never
become a ראשון rishon as far as חולין chulin are concerned. רבי
שמעון בן אלעזר אומר משום רבי מאיר, Rebbi Shimon ben Elazar omer
mishum Rebbi Meir, he says in the name of רבי מאיר, Rebbi
Meir, ידיים תחלות לחולין ושניות לתרומה. yadayim techilot lechulin veshniyot leterumah.
Your hands can become a ראשון rishon for חולין chulin and they
can even become
a שני sheni for תרומה. Truma. Now we have not yet said
what the circumstances are. I'll just jump ahead a little bit and
tell you what the circumstances are because I know it's bothering Michael.
You have a house where there's צרעת. tzara'at. If I were to
enter into that house I would be טמא. tamei. Let's say I
just stuck my hands in. Now it's not considered like I've entered
in. If it were considered I entered in I would completely become
טמא, tamei, but rabbinic Technically they're going to say my hands are
טמא. tamei. And the question is what level are they going to
be? On the one hand, if the house was צרעת, tzara'at, which
is an אב, av, the source, we should say a source the
next level is that they become a ראשון. rishon. So that's a
logical idea to say your hands at least rabbinically are ראשון. rishon.
On the other hand, we could say no, when we have a
model of rabbinic טומאה tum'ah as we said before, it's always a
שני. sheni. So if we're going to make your hands a problem,
we're going to make them a שני; sheni; we're not going to
make them a ראשון. rishon. So this is a debate: can we
have this idea of hand being a ראשון? rishon? In case... so
right, we're going to say, in a case where they are a
ראשון, rishon, if you believe that such a phenomenon exists, like you
stuck your hands in a בית מנוגע beit menuga and they're considered
a ראשון rishon not a שני, sheni, that's the case in our
משנה mishna that if the meat were susceptible, you would make the
meat טמא, tamei, and because there is no blood, you don't make
it טמא. tamei. When you wash your hands, because it's only טומאה
tum'ah of the hands, that's why you can wash it with the
cup and make them טהור tahor and exactly, that's part of this
whole rabbinic model. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this:
okay, דתניא, detanya, אין ידיים תחילה לחולין, ein yadayim techilah l'chulin,
hands cannot be a ראשון rishon vis-a-vis חולין. chulin. If hands are
a problem, they're going to be a שני sheni or nothing. רבי
שמעון בן אלעזר אומר, Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer, but רבי שמעון
בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar says משום mishum d'Rabbi Meir, no,
ידיים תחילות לחולין, yadayim techilos l'chulin, there can be scenarios where a
hand does become a ראשון rishon and does have an impact for
חולין. chulin. ושניות, u'sheniyos, and then there are other scenarios where your
hands are a שני sheni לתרומה, l'trumah, and that has a relevance
for תרומה. trumah. So the גמרא Gemara says, תחילות לחולין אין לתרומה
לאו, techilos l'chulin in, l'trumah lav, when you say they're a ראשון,
rishon, what? It only has relevance to חולין chulin and not to
תרומה? trumah? No, הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, this is what it means:
תחילות אף לחולין. techilos af l'chulin. There are cases where your hands
become a ראשון, rishon, and then they can impact even חולין. chulin.
Of course they can impact תרומה, trumah, but they can even impact
חולין. chulin. ושניות, u'sheniyos, but when they become a second, when you're
in the standard case when your hands are a שני, sheni, לתרומה,
l'trumah, אין לחולין לא. in l'chulin lo. Then they can only impact
תרומה, trumah, not חולין. chulin. So now we are saying there is
a phenomenon according to רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar
of hands being a ראשון. rishon. Okay, ומי איכא ידיים תחילות? u'mika
yadayim techilos? Where is such a phenomenon exist?
אין, in, yes. דתנן, detnan, we taught in the משנה, mishna, הכניס
ידו לבית המנוגע, hichnis yado l'veit hamenuga, if you stuck your hands
into a house with צרעת, tzara'at, with leprosy, ידיו תחילות, yadav techilos,
your hands are a ראשון. rishon. דברי רבי עקיבא, divrei Rabbi Akiva,
that's what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says. So, like we said before,
and that has relevance even for חולין, chulin, like we said by
רבי שמעון בן אלעזר. Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar. וחכמים אומרים, vachachamim omrim,
but the sages say, ידיו שניות, yadav sheniyos, your hands are a
שני. sheni. And now we're going to explain what this debate is.
דכולי עלמא, d'chulei alma, ביאה במקצת לא שמה ביאה. bia b'miktzat lo
shmah bia. Everybody agrees going in with part of your body is
not like you entered in the house. If we were to say
going in with your hand is like you entered, your whole person
would be טמא tamei as a ראשון. rishon. So we have to
say both positions hold you... it's not like you entered. So biblically
it's nothing. But rabbinically we're not going to ignore the fact that
your hands were in the house. Okay, והכא בגזירה ידיו אטו גופו
קמיפלגי. v'hacha b'gzeira yadav atu gufo kamifligi. And here the reason your
hands are טמא tamei is we're going to make a safeguard that
we're not going to let... that your hands will lead to your
whole body, meaning everybody agrees that rabbinically we can't let this go.
We can't turn a blind eye to this. If you stuck your
hands in, there have to be some implications, because if there aren't
implications, next thing you know, you'll be walking in with your whole
body into the house. So maybe, but we're not talking about that
right now. Okay, because maybe there's not a concept of, you know,
when the only time we have a concept of טומאה tum'ah on
limited body parts is by hands. So that's the... you know, we're
not going to totally break those molds.
I understand. All right, I understand. Anyway, but because your hands are,
we can't turn a blind eye to that, or else next thing
you know you'll be going in yourself. We have to make your
hands טמא. tamei. And the question is, what model did we use
to make your hands טמא? tamei? Logically, it should be a ראשון,
rishon, because they entered into a house, a source of טומאה. tum'ah.
But maybe we don't have such a model of hands being a
ראשון. rishon. Right? Either your whole body could be a ראשון, rishon,
but just hands, classically that's a שני. sheni. So let's take a
look. מר סבר, mar savar, one holds ידיים כגופו שבינהו רבנן, yadayim
k'gufo shavinhu rabanan, that your hands are like your body. If your
body had entered in, it would be a ראשון, rishon, so here
we're going to make your hands a ראשון. rishon. That's רבי עקיבא.
Rabbi Akiva. ומר סבר, u'mar savar, the other opinion is no, ידיים
כידיים דעלמא שבינהו רבנן. yadayim k'yadayim d'alma shavinhu rabanan. No, they made
hands... if they're going to say your hands are טמא, tamei, same
like Michael said, they're not going to say your foot is טמא.
tamei. They're going to say your hands are טמא. tamei. It's only
because there already exists a rabbinic concept of טומאה tum'ah just on
the hands. But that rabbinic concept of טומאה tum'ah just on the
hands is that your hands being a שני, sheni, not a ראשון.
rishon. Okay, so whew, where are we with all of this? We
are that the משנה mishna says the meat is not susceptible, therefore
you can touch it. If it were susceptible, well you could touch
it, but it would become טמא. tamei. Why is it טמא? tamei?
Your hands are a שני, sheni, the meat can't be a שלישי,
shlishi, it's חולין. chulin. So the answer is, no, we're assuming like
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that it's a scenario where your hands are
a ראשון, rishon, they entered into a בית מנוגע, beit menuga, your
hands are a ראשון, rishon, and therefore they can make the meat
into a שני. sheni. But because it doesn't have blood and it's
not susceptible, that's what the משנה mishna is talking about. So now
the גמרא Gemara just wraps this up. ולוקמה כרבי עקיבא דאמר ידיו
תחילות הויין? v'lokma k'Rabbi Akiva d'amar yadav techilos havyan? No, so why
did you jump to רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון? Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon?
Why don't you just say רבי עקיבא? Rabbi Akiva? רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva explicitly discusses the idea of your hands becoming a ראשון. rishon.
Now, so דילמא כי קאמר רבי עקיבא, dilma ki ka'amar Rebbe Akiva,
maybe when did רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva say your hands are ראשון?
rishon? הני מילי בתרומה ובקדשים. hani milei bi-terumah u-bikdashim. Maybe that would
be relevant if your hands touched תרומה terumah or sanctified objects דחמירי
di-chamiri which are strict, אבל בחולין שני הוי. aval bi-chulin sheini havi.
Maybe he would say that even when he makes your hands a
ראשון, rishon, maybe he would say only in the world of תרומה
terumah and sacrifices, but in the world of non-sanctified objects, your hands
will never have that degree, that severity.
But we know that רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rebbe Eleazar b'Rebbe Shimon
explicitly said that in scenarios where your hands are a ראשון, rishon,
they will impact even חולין. chulin. So that's why we said he
could be the author of our משנה. mishna. A special case where
your hands are a ראשון, rishon, he says that that impacts even
חולין, chulin, and חולין chulin we know can become a שני, sheini,
and that's the case of our משנה mishna why it was important
to say that the meat did not become susceptible. Let me just
see what time it is. Okay, we have one minute, so let's
just finish
up. שני הוי וליהוי נמי שני. sheini havi v'leihavi nami sheini. Now,
you know what, we'll end here. So to be continued tomorrow and
don't say you weren't warned because this is going to be all
of the discussion tomorrow.